<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[J. Ryan Stinnett]]></title>
  <link href="http://convolv.es/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://convolv.es/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-17T23:14:41-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://convolv.es/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[J. Ryan Stinnett]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Into the Open]]></title>
    <link href="http://convolv.es/blog/2013/02/17/into-the-open/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-17T22:52:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://convolv.es/blog/2013/02/17/into-the-open</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m excited to start to focusing what time I do have on the side towards open
source projects.  I&#8217;m always on the lookout for good projects to help out with,
but these days I always seem to come back to web browsers.</p>

<p>In particular, I really enjoy working on tools that improve the lives of other
every day.  In that vein, I&#8217;d like to focus on improvements to the developer
tools in browsers today, though they are vastly better today than even a few
years ago.</p>

<p>The main open source options as far as web browsers go are Chrome / Chromium and
the various Mozilla projects, like Firefox. Near the end of 2011, I started
ramping up on the Chromium project, mainly because Chrome is the main browser I
used then.</p>

<p>However, now that Opera has decided to switch to Chromium for future versions of
their browser, I&#8217;ve been reminded that Mozilla is the only party in the web
development game that truly seems to be doing their best to fight for the user.
The main reason I stopped using Firefox was due to Chrome&#8217;s impressive developer
tools, so I&#8217;d like to help improve Firefox tools to bring them up to the level
we&#8217;ve now come to expect and beyond.</p>

<p>Likely I&#8217;ll dabble in both Chromium and Firefox, but no matter what it should be
an exciting time ahead!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Materials, Maps, and Surfacing]]></title>
    <link href="http://convolv.es/blog/2012/10/06/materials/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-06T15:13:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://convolv.es/blog/2012/10/06/materials</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Overview</h3>

<p>For this <a href="http://viscom3d.blogspot.com/2012/09/materials-maps-and-surfacing.html">assignment</a>, we learned how to apply materials to the objects
we&#8217;ve been creating.  There are many, many different ways to construct a
material that you apply to 3D object.  They can be procedurally generated, they
can pull from textures (or maps) you create, and you can manually tune many
parameters as well.</p>

<p>Maps are a great way to control the appearance of an object because you can make
something resemble a real object quite quickly by just taking a picture and
doing a bit of editing.</p>

<h3>Environment</h3>

<p>For the environment, I used a variety of wood textures as maps to give the huts
a rustic feel.  The door particularly look much more believable now.  Also, the
islands look much less like strange brains now there&#8217;s a grassy appearance
applied, instead of just the flat green.</p>

<p><img src="http://convolv.es/images/posts/env-mat.png" alt="Env 1" /></p>

<h3>Robot</h3>

<p>For the robot, I gave him a weathered, rusty metal appearance that seems to tie
in well with his supportive / charming look. Old, but still functioning just
fine.</p>

<p>The eyes and mouth have a bit of an ethereal / floating feel to them thanks to
the transparency.</p>

<p>It was fun to experiment with the various parameters and material types that can
give a metallic appearance.</p>

<p><img src="http://convolv.es/images/posts/robot-mat.png" alt="Robot 1" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Splines, Loft, and Lathe]]></title>
    <link href="http://convolv.es/blog/2012/09/29/splines/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-29T08:17:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://convolv.es/blog/2012/09/29/splines</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Overview</h3>

<p>For this <a href="http://viscom3d.blogspot.com/2012/09/spline-modeling-and-compound-objects.html">assignment</a>, we learned a few new techniques, namely how to make
use of 2D shapes to give more detail to our models.  Beyond simple shapes like
circles and squares is the very flexible spline, which gives you a lot of
control over how a line is drawn, while still be purely analytical.</p>

<h3>Shapes and Splines</h3>

<p>For part of the homework, we added some shapes and splines to our existing
models.  Below you can see the island huts from before, but with a few
additional decorations, such as some scary wiring / branches, as well as door
knobs and roof ornaments.</p>

<p><img src="http://convolv.es/images/posts/env-ss1.png" alt="Env 1" />
<img src="http://convolv.es/images/posts/env-ss2.png" alt="Env 2" />
<img src="http://convolv.es/images/posts/env-ss3.png" alt="Env 3" /></p>

<h3>Lathe and Loft</h3>

<p>We also learned how to take 2D paths and morph them into 3D shapes in several
interesting ways.  You can use lathe to revolve the path around an axis, similar
to a torus.</p>

<p>I used this technique to create a pot, an inflatable pool, and a spyglass.</p>

<p><img src="http://convolv.es/images/posts/lathe.png" alt="Lathe" /></p>

<p>We also learned about loft, which will take a shape and replicate it in 3D
across whatever path you define.  This is another very powerful feature, with
many ways you can customize and tune its behavior.</p>

<p>I made several tracks and other shapes using this process:</p>

<p><img src="http://convolv.es/images/posts/loft1.png" alt="Loft 1" />
<img src="http://convolv.es/images/posts/loft2.png" alt="Loft 2" />
<img src="http://convolv.es/images/posts/loft3.png" alt="Loft 3" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Basic Game with Unity]]></title>
    <link href="http://convolv.es/blog/2012/09/22/basic-game-with-unity/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-22T04:42:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://convolv.es/blog/2012/09/22/basic-game-with-unity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Overview</h3>

<p>For this week&#8217;s <a href="http://viscom3d.blogspot.com/2012/09/unity-101.html">assignment</a>, we jumped out of the normal curriculum and
went straight to using a game engine with our models from last time.  We added a
few common elements, like terrain and fog.</p>

<h3>Unity</h3>

<p>Unity is a lot of fun to work with! It&#8217;s quite easy to assemble something pretty
cool, and yet it is also has a lot of depth to allow you to refine details. I
can definitely see myself working with this down the road, especially given the
wide multi-platform support.</p>

<h3>Game Level</h3>

<p>For the level itself, I modified the environment to remove the static water I
made before and surround the island with mountainous terrain.  Then I added the
animated water to get back to the original environment idea.</p>

<p>From there, I added some basic lighting and fog to match the skybox I chose.  It
was actually a bit tricky to map a collider to the island huts.  For now I used
spheres, but perhaps I&#8217;ll need to flatten those into a single mesh for Unity to
represent them accurately.</p>

<p>There&#8217;s definitely room for improvement along many aspects, but it&#8217;s really
exciting to see something playable come together so quickly.</p>

<p><img src="http://convolv.es/images/posts/level1.png" alt="Level 1" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[3D Modeling: Robot in the Ruins]]></title>
    <link href="http://convolv.es/blog/2012/09/15/3d-modeling-robot-in-the-ruins/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-15T05:43:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://convolv.es/blog/2012/09/15/3d-modeling-robot-in-the-ruins</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Overview</h3>

<p>For our <a href="http://viscom3d.blogspot.com/2012/01/robot-in-ruins.html">first assignment</a>, we had to build a robot and an environment for the it to inhabit.</p>

<h3>Robot</h3>

<p>The robot had to use exactly 1000 polygons. I chose to create a kind of
transport robot with a cute appearance. I used an elongated egg shape, and gave
it two propellers to maneuver. The robot is shown at an angle to suggest
movement.  The propellers were fun to construct, especially with the primitives,
since you have to think of clever ways to build what want from just a few
shapes. With two shapes and a few filters, I arrived at a convincing version of
propeller blades.</p>

<p><img src="http://convolv.es/images/posts/robot1.png" alt="Robot 1" />
<img src="http://convolv.es/images/posts/robot2.png" alt="Robot 2" />
<img src="http://convolv.es/images/posts/robot3.png" alt="Robot 3" /></p>

<h3>Environment</h3>

<p>For the environment, we had a budget of 10,000 polygons. I thought it would be
fun to create a water / island environment. However, even a poor simulation of
water quickly eats up a lot of polygons!</p>

<p>My thoughts here were that several of the robots might be used to transport
various items between the islands as needed.</p>

<p><img src="http://convolv.es/images/posts/env1.png" alt="Environment 1" />
<img src="http://convolv.es/images/posts/env2.png" alt="Environment 2" />
<img src="http://convolv.es/images/posts/env3.png" alt="Environment 3" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[3D Modeling and Rendering 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://convolv.es/blog/2012/09/07/3d-modeling-and-rendering-1/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-07T23:20:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://convolv.es/blog/2012/09/07/3d-modeling-and-rendering-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve started taking classes at ACC to learn some visual design skills and
generally extend my knowledge of how games and other media are built.</p>

<p>The first one is this 3D modeling class, and I&#8217;ll be maintaining a portfolio of
my work as this class goes on. I&#8217;m excited to see what I can come up with!
Undoubtedly my work won&#8217;t win too many awards, but hopefully I can pick up the
principles and develop them further over time.</p>

<p>I think this will also give me a better understanding of the thought process that
design and creative teams go through at the various places I&#8217;ve worked now and in
the past.</p>

<p>Anyway, should be fun! :D</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exciting new blog thing]]></title>
    <link href="http://convolv.es/blog/2012/05/07/exciting-new-blog-thing/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-07T23:28:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://convolv.es/blog/2012/05/07/exciting-new-blog-thing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&#8230;to replace what exactly? My LiveJournal from college&#8230;? I&#8217;ve never been great at maintaining any kind of journal / blog / whatever, but <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> just looks like so much fun, so I had to give it a shot. Tonight I finally ripped the default theme up a bit to create a more minimalist look, which I think turned out quite well.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m hoping to start talking about all the crazy tech projects I&#8217;ve got brewing in my mind that I&#8217;ll one day sit down and make progress on, along with a few bits of life, work, and everything else mixed in.</p>

<p>Even writing this tiny thing is more than I&#8217;ve done in ages. Any guesses how long until the next one?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
