<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Developer Tools | J. Ryan Stinnett]]></title>
  <link href="http://convolv.es/blog/categories/developer-tools/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://convolv.es/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-04T00:45:51-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://convolv.es/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[J. Ryan Stinnett]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <icon>http://convolv.es/favicon.ico</icon>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mozilla]]></title>
    <link href="http://convolv.es/blog/2013/08/25/mozilla/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-25T01:27:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://convolv.es/blog/2013/08/25/mozilla</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my <a href="/blog/2013/02/17/into-the-open/">last post</a> (back in February...), I mentioned I was spending a lot of
time on the side working on the developer tools in web browsers, particularly
Firefox.  I find that Mozilla's values, which truly put the user first, are
something I agree with wholeheartedly.  Mozilla is in a unique position in this
way, since all the other browsers are made by companies that, at the end of day,
are looking to make money to appease their shareholders.  Mozilla's values are
even more important to emphasize these days with the various forms of
governmental spying that has been revealed in the last few months.</p>

<p>With that context, hopefully you can get an idea of how excited I am to say that
this past Monday was my first day as a Mozilla employee, working on the Firefox
Developer Tools team!</p>

<p>I am currently in Paris ramping up with the team for two weeks.  After the first
week, I am humbled to be able to say I am a part of this organization.  There
are so many people smarter than me here, and I am thrilled to have the
opportunity to work with them.  I know we will accomplish great things together.</p>

<p>There is so much potential in the web developer tools space.  Every developer
has their own workflow, favorite set of frameworks and tools, and new platform
technologies and techniques are coming out at a rapid pace.  While part of my
job is certainly to help make all of this more efficient, there is a lot of room
to shake things up by looking towards the future of web development and the
tools that people don't even know they need.</p>

<p>It's going to be a blast! Hopefully I'll have to some fun things to share.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
