<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Firefox for Android on J. Ryan Stinnett</title>
    <link>https://convolv.es/blog/tags/firefox-for-android/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Firefox for Android on J. Ryan Stinnett</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2015 15:33:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://convolv.es/blog/tags/firefox-for-android/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item xml:base="https://convolv.es/blog/2015/08/05/wifi-debug-fennec/">
      <title>WiFi Debugging for Firefox for Android</title>
      <link>https://convolv.es/blog/2015/08/05/wifi-debug-fennec/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2015 15:33:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://convolv.es/blog/2015/08/05/wifi-debug-fennec/</guid>
      <description>I am excited to announce that we&amp;rsquo;re now shipping WiFi debugging for Firefox for Android! It&amp;rsquo;s available in Firefox for Android 42 with Firefox Nightly on desktop.
The rest of this post will sound quite similar to the previous announcement for Firefox OS support.
WiFi debugging allows WebIDE to connect to Firefox for Android via your local WiFi network instead of a USB cable.
The connection experience is generally more straightforward (especially after connecting to a device the first time) than with USB and also more convenient to use since you&amp;rsquo;re no longer tied down by a cable.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am excited to announce that we&rsquo;re now <a href="https://bugzil.la/1180996">shipping</a> WiFi debugging for
Firefox for Android!  It&rsquo;s available in <a href="https://nightly.mozilla.org/">Firefox for Android 42</a>
with <a href="https://nightly.mozilla.org/">Firefox Nightly</a> on desktop.</p>
<p>The rest of this post will sound quite similar to the <a href="/blog/2015/03/25/wifi-debug-fxos/">previous announcement for
Firefox OS</a> support.</p>
<p>WiFi debugging allows <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/docs/Tools/WebIDE">WebIDE</a> to connect to Firefox for Android via
your local WiFi network instead of a USB cable.</p>
<p>The connection experience is generally more straightforward (especially after
connecting to a device the first time) than with USB and also more convenient to
use since you&rsquo;re no longer tied down by a cable.</p>
<h2 id="security">Security</h2>
<p>A large portion of this project has gone towards making the debugging
connection secure, so that you can use it safely on shared network, such as an
office or coffee shop.</p>
<p>We use TLS for encryption and authentication.  The computer and device both
create self-signed certificates.  When you connect, a QR code is scanned to
verify that the certificates can be trusted.  During the connection process, you
can choose to remember this information and connect immediately in the future if
desired.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-use">How to Use</h2>
<p>You&rsquo;ll need to assemble the following bits and bobs:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://nightly.mozilla.org/">Firefox 42</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nightly.mozilla.org/">Firefox for Android 42</a></li>
<li><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.google.zxing.client.android">Barcode Scanner Android app by ZXing Team</a> (for QR code scanning)</li>
</ul>
<p>On your Android device:</p>
<ol>
<li>Install the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.google.zxing.client.android">Barcode Scanner Android app by ZXing Team</a></li>
<li>Open Firefox for Android</li>
<li>Go to Developer Tools Settings on device (Settings -&gt; Developer Tools)</li>
<li>Enable Remote Debugging via Wi-Fi</li>
</ol>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="fennec-wifi-opts.png" alt="Firefox for Android WiFi Debugging Options"  />
</p>
<p>To connect from Firefox Desktop:</p>
<ol>
<li>Open WebIDE in Firefox Nightly (Tools -&gt; Web Developer -&gt; WebIDE)</li>
<li>Click &ldquo;Select Runtime&rdquo; to open the runtimes panel</li>
<li>Your Firefox for Android device should show up in the &ldquo;WiFi Devices&rdquo; section</li>
<li>A connection prompt will appear on device, choose &ldquo;Scan&rdquo; or &ldquo;Scan and Remember&rdquo;</li>
<li>Scan the QR code displayed in WebIDE</li>
</ol>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="webide-wifi-runtime.png" alt="WebIDE WiFi Runtimes"  />

<img loading="lazy" src="webide-qr-code.png" alt="WebIDE Displays the QR Code"  />
</p>
<p>After scanning the QR code, the QR display should disappear and the &ldquo;device&rdquo;
icon in WebIDE will turn blue for &ldquo;connected&rdquo;.</p>
<p>You can then access all of your remote browser tabs just as you can today over
USB.</p>
<h2 id="technical-aside">Technical Aside</h2>
<p>This process does not use ADB at all on the device, so if you find ADB
inconvenient while debugging or would rather not install ADB at all, then
WiFi debugging is the way to go.</p>
<p>By skipping ADB, we don&rsquo;t have to worry about driver confusion, especially on
Windows and Linux.</p>
<h2 id="supported-devices">Supported Devices</h2>
<p>This feature should be supported on any Firefox for Android device.  So far,
I&rsquo;ve tested it on the LG G2.</p>
<h2 id="acknowledgments">Acknowledgments</h2>
<p>Thanks to all who helped via advice and reviews while working on Android support,
including (in semi-random order):</p>
<ul>
<li>Margaret Leibovic</li>
<li>Karim Benhmida</li>
</ul>
<p>And from the larger WiFi debugging effort:</p>
<ul>
<li>Brian Warner</li>
<li>Trevor Perrin</li>
<li>David Keeler</li>
<li>Honza Bambas</li>
<li>Patrick McManus</li>
<li>Jason Duell</li>
<li>Panos Astithas</li>
<li>Jan Keromnes</li>
<li>Alexandre Poirot</li>
<li>Paul Rouget</li>
<li>Paul Theriault</li>
</ul>
<p>I am probably forgetting others as well, so I apologize if you were omitted.</p>
<h2 id="whats-next">What&rsquo;s Next</h2>
<p>If there are features you&rsquo;d like to see added, <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=Firefox&amp;component=Developer%20Tools%3A%20WebIDE">file bugs</a> or contact the
team via <a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/DevTools/GetInvolved#Communication">various channels</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item xml:base="https://convolv.es/blog/2014/10/28/debug-fennec-tabs/">
      <title>Debugging Tabs with Firefox for Android</title>
      <link>https://convolv.es/blog/2014/10/28/debug-fennec-tabs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2014 16:08:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://convolv.es/blog/2014/10/28/debug-fennec-tabs/</guid>
      <description>For quite a while, it has been possible to debug tabs on Firefox for Android devices, but there were many steps involved, including manual port forwarding from the terminal.
As I hinted a few weeks ago, WebIDE would soon support connecting to Firefox for Android via ADB Helper support, and that time is now!
How to Use You&amp;rsquo;ll need to assemble the following bits and bobs:
Firefox 36 (2014-10-25 or later) ADB Helper 0.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For quite a while, it has been possible to debug tabs on Firefox for Android
devices, but there were many steps involved, including manual port forwarding
from the terminal.</p>
<p>As I <a href="/blog/2014/10/14/debug-fxos-tabs/">hinted</a> a few weeks ago, <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/docs/Tools/WebIDE">WebIDE</a> would soon support connecting
to Firefox for Android via ADB Helper support, and that time is now!</p>
<h2 id="how-to-use">How to Use</h2>
<p>You&rsquo;ll need to assemble the following bits and bobs:</p>
<ul>
<li>Firefox 36 (2014-10-25 or later)</li>
<li>ADB Helper 0.7.0 or later</li>
<li>Firefox for Android 35 or later</li>
</ul>
<p>Opening WebIDE for the first time should install ADB Helper if you don&rsquo;t already
have it, but double-check it is the right version in the add-on manager.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="fennec-usb-runtime.png" alt="Firefox for Android runtime appears"  />
</p>
<p>Inside WebIDE, you&rsquo;ll see an entry for Firefox for Android in the Runtime menu.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="fennec-tab-list.png" alt="Firefox for Android tab list"  />
</p>
<p>Once you select the runtime, tabs from Firefox for Android will be available in
the (now poorly labelled) apps menu on the left.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="fennec-tab-toolbox.png" alt="Inspecting a tab in WebIDE"  />
</p>
<p>Choosing a tab will open up the DevTools toolbox for that tab.  You can also
toggle the toolbox via the &ldquo;Pause&rdquo; icon in the top toolbar.</p>
<p>If you would like to debug Firefox for Android&rsquo;s system-level / chrome code,
instead of a specific tab, you can do that with the &ldquo;Main Process&rdquo; option.</p>
<h2 id="whats-next">What&rsquo;s Next</h2>
<p>We have even more connection UX improvements on the way, so I hope to have more
to share soon!</p>
<p>If there are features you&rsquo;d like to see added, <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=Firefox&amp;component=Developer%20Tools%3A%20WebIDE">file bugs</a> or contact the
team via <a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/DevTools/GetInvolved#Communication">various channels</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
